I was working on dated a little bit with
young static list when I saw Jordan the
first time I remembered Jordan from the
90s when maps meaning came out and ice
looked at the guy in YouTube and I just
thought yeah of course a guy like that
is the next superstar Jordan piers yeah
he's perfect for it he's this university
lecturer he's really good at teaching
it's good very thoughtful way presenting
himself very clever very very sort of
priestly fatherly figure to him made a
lot of sense right so and he took the
struggle with the social justice
warriors and the completely
misunderstood him which meant that he
would win he would definitely beat them
right and and he's never been
pretentious I love Jordan to bits and I
love him precisely because never - he's
never pretended to be anything he's not
yeah indeed yeah yeah and I the way I'm
reacted to was that I told Peter I work
with Peter that's great because normally
when you write a philosophical work you
hope somebody else is gonna do the pop
version of it oh you like do you think
Peterson is a pop version of you yes but
he was there already before we published
a book yeah okay we had published
Cynthia was causing a stir and we were
working I did is a liberal and suddenly
Jordan was dead I was just like what
we're gonna write about and digital
liberal the mass infantilization of
contemporary society you know the the
horrors of the welfare state and a
consumer society and the big mistake we
made even Hitler installed and you know
assuming what what Eva was and all that
all the knowns as we had the last 100
years all the crap ideology we need to
deal with roll up and understand how
actually pathologically disoriented we
are all of the stuff yeah Jordan does
that so well just as so well he points
exactly the same good pointing and he
gets all the guys going he gets them
going on their own personal journeys to
what I understand what we're doing so
when we really stay just a little bit
just like yeah we're gonna be the second
way you ever gonna be smaller there are
fewer people
we gotta reach the people who who
interested in the real depth and the
widening where do we go next
you know and then Jordan can work with
that later I hope when he's off the tour
gets to have some time of his own when
in northern Canada and the cabin and
start thinking again because think
Jordan can come back and really be the
brilliant philosopher - not just an
artist or a psychologist philosopher I
think he needs to take time off after
all this popularity is over done with as
well yeah well because I always enjoy
listening to him but once you've learned
the his feel right you just just listen
to it in different ways and so so it's
it's becoming he's becoming a bit
repetitive and that's normal because
he's like on tour all the time so it's
like a it's like a rock band trying to
play the same yeah you can only say that
even if you get on Andrew Sweeney's
podcast or do podcast under Sweeney
that's better than any other part
because you'll never do well you cannot
really get to the depth you can get to
in a text which is much more dense late
so lectures podcast webcast can only get
to that for then you need to go to the
books and I tell all the guys South yeah
you can read 12 rules for life it's the
best self probably ever written but at
the end of the day maps of meaning is
this really profound works that's the
real of Jordan so you want you want the
maps of meaning Jordan back after all
this is over and he could do great work
essentially to me it is Tessa there are
three types of storytelling in the
original tribe there's the magical
storytelling which is that everything
returns to the same and that's what we
remember from kindergarten that's the
stories you tell the kids but it's also
the true and on a story about the tribe
itself so it's both a story for grownups
and for kids but it's a story for
grown-ups to tell us you you are born
you you manage to fool yourself into
thinking you want to live you get a
little you see the parents around you or
the older people around you and your kid
you want even one of them and one day
you become a grown-up you get the
respect and the autonomy that goes with
that then you get responsibility which
is wonderful you come back to the tribe
you deliver on that
possibility do you give birth to a child
or you bring back an animal you just
hunted but you do contribute to the
tribe you get your own value then when
you get older you have less of an ego
and some you're more interested in
what's gonna follow you and you start
training the young you become a mentor
one day you might even become an elderly
if you're lucky enough because you lived
a full life and your wisdom and your
smile and your warm eyes with everybody
else yes and you just give back and you
give back until you completely exhausted
and you don't feel you have anything to
give back in this new generation ready
take over even for you being an elderly
and that's when you die and then you die
happily yeah you don't really die having
lived a whole life not a perfect whole
this is you okay so this is the magical
story Jordan does that really well the
second story being told this difference
between the two different stores that
are phallic remember I talked about you
got the king and the priest and they're
separate
yeah King in the song God won't know the
king and the rain God and you got the
priest in the Sun go their separate keep
Patrick is separate because we don't
want the tyrant okay so one of them
stands for truth that's what Jordan
tries did himself he's just that and
that's a man always stand up and speak
the truth with integrity and with
courage yeah that's what the priest has
to do the priest must speak the truth at
all times otherwise he's useless as a
brain that's his only masculine that is
his masculine right and he's got the
monks and the other guys too supporting
me doing that then you got the chieftain
and he leads by being true that's called
truth as an act he's true through his
actions he does the right thing it's
like extrovert introvert if we're
talking about young in a sense you could
say that he lead he leads forward to
meets Hegel and Nietzsche you know Hegel
is the philosopher all the chief tenets
of loss over the priests in this answer
that's what they do
so you lead by example you it's called
truth that's an act in our work you you
act the truth that's he become truthful
you order speaks less about that but
maybe born ascetic let's do it even more
so so but these are the two different
truths in fact that means we have to
remember it then in the solarium
the garage boom with two different
stories being told one story is the
purely factual one that's what science
is supposed to aim for it's called a
shot interestin ism how things work
meaning when you go hunting this is how
you sharpen your weapons these are the
weapons you need these are the weapons
that are too heavy to carry or these are
the weapons that are perfectly able to
carry these are the ones that you like
not very useful you learn everything
about materials you learn everything
about measurement you learn everything
you need to know so your team goes out
there you optimize your chances of
success now if you don't warfare even
more so you need a whole team you need
the drawing board you need to know where
your really sources are the guy who wins
the world's met this guy who knows
exactly what he's doing
that's called factual reality that means
factuality is originally from the
military it was inherited by modern
science and science should at least be
preoccupied with that that's one type of
storytelling storytelling of Mathematics
and footnotes okay but there's an AB
story in tow which is the one the door
is broken by winds called mythology
mm-hmm okay where does me solid yorker
me solid your curse starting in the
afternoon imagine you got the Mack truck
and the pair jority of the priests they
meet and they're very concerned because
they know that if the tribe doesn't get
moving tomorrow morning they'll all die
okay then the Patrick in the Metra tells
the phrase you need to tell the tribe
that the old falter has told the Patrick
that he needs to get going and all the
guys need to follow him and then you
need to tell them that the bull mother
has told the man charged the she needs
to push everybody ahead of her and if
they don't follow her orders and move
they will die so you needed to tell the
story about the remoter and the old
falter factor having told us this story
now this is the thing
ask the priest as to shame and it tells
the story after sundown and before the
ground gets cold and evening that's when
we do tabloid television that's when we
all get together and close it on after
six o'clock meaning we have an evening
meal at 7 o clock until 10 o'clock we're
good
this is the most crucial time of the day
because this is the time of narrative
was Thomas storytelling biologically
pre-programmed in each one of us in the
tribes this would be three steps forward
by the fire and he tells a story and
this is the thing about his story he's
allowed to use any trick in the book as
long as it gets the desired effect which
is that the tribe moose the next morning
okay
the tribe it doesn't do this dies the
tribe that dusty successfully survives
and after hundreds of thousands of years
we did it pretty sure that the self is
tribe wins not the selfish gene and the
selfish trial that wins is the one that
has a formidable priest does a brilliant
narrative and leaning real story can be
fantastic fantastic anything maybe
Bibles you know weird stuff but
dinosaurs whales just don't care this is
the thing with mythology mythology is
not ever to be interpreted literally as
a fundamentalist of all kinds of Rome
the point we Jordan is that this story
can be any story but it's the morality
of the story it's the effect of the
story that counts and it's a social
biological evolutionary phenomena this
is why the grand narrative is so
important today and the tough work we
need to do we need both the factual
story about reality which is science
needs to get there or we need to create
new Sciences do the job so what you're
saying if I could just have a neatly
simplistic here you're saying we need
art and science right I mean yes what I
do what I do is that I'm a philosopher I
work on grand narratives I work on how
you build them what is necessary how are
they different from one another
what is the work we need to do so I'm
basically advising the priesthood saying
okay this is what you need to know this
is the kind of story in itself at that
moment this is the factual story you
tell the soldiers to leave the tribe in
the morning this system it's a logical
story it tells seven about the meaning
we all must also now tell people they
must not interfere and mix these two
stories or they get totally confused too
they lose completely so I rather work
with young novelists hey young artists
and inspire them because they
do something different from what I do
rather than just working young
philosophers who just compliment my work
and add something to it mm-hmm
that makes sense right and if you look
at the guys around Jordan and little
intellectual deep web now in North
America and Europe and the people
popping up behind the dark web they're
all young guys girls and guys who are
interested in writing novels and doing
computer games and do art and I do
basically tell you're allowed to use any
medium you like cause it's three o'clock
in the afternoon
hmm but you need to understand and get
it on the move tomorrow morning yeah you
got to get your story out there sort of
thing yeah the best example of a culture
to dust that is Russia because in Russia
the novelists because of the Tsar the
Philosopher's couldn't speak freely and
the novelist could in a clever way speak
is truthfully as the philosophers did
that's exactly what Jordan loved
Solzhenitsyn he lost also he lost the
Russian novelist because Russia is a
culture where the novel was more true
than philosophy oh yeah he says he says
it's more true than true right that's
not a good novelist like that ecology is
compressed truth also hidden truth or it
catches the attention of way more people
than my damn philosophy books every
world and I'm highly respectful of the
novelist high respectful artist that's
exactly why philosophers obsessed with
novelist and they're assessed with art
isn't the one inspire aren't because art
can reach more people in an emotional
matter but belongs to be sets the rules
so it seems like in the first half of
your life you're engaged in art and now
you're getting the second half you're
engaged in philosophy right well which
recipe but archetype you've got a
secondary argument that's that's a
that's kind of a Jungian thing right a
bit you know he said you know the
morning of your life where you eat you
experiment and you do wild things and
you you you know you go in every
direction and then the last stop you
like you synthesize that you you you
articulate what it all meant in some
kind of a way and we all know that when
we turn 40 we get a last chance to
completely change direction in our lives
yeah okay
we have two archetypes yeah well as a
universal happens with people who turned
40 everywhere and most cultures people
live beyond 40 probably lived until they
were 70 there between 40 and 70 is
usually not make sick and die okay so
why are sudden switch in a totally
different direction that means the vast
majority people have to architects when
you study college in Canada American you
do a major and you do minor right that's
a clever way of putting it
the primary archetype is that which you
do with EES that still impresses other
people yes those things you just do yeah
it's easiest thing in the world
everybody else cuz Wow not for us no not
for the rest of us no fucking women that
well no no no no no you're a stud you do
better than us really yeah primary
archetype okay reading books yeah I
can't help myself I read books all the
terms and what are you doing your spare
time I pick up a book I pick up books Oh
read read read read primary architect
easiest thing in the world for me to do
and then maybe I even write one one day
but I absorbed text I love it yeah I'm
marking up for you Andrew you're great
the microphone see great cameras you've
got a warm curiosity of you also learned
from the very beginning meaning having
conversation we use a wonderful thing
primary archetype you're the perfect
modern medium columnist journalist and
whatever that medium expands you
probably do well with it because it's
your primary archetype you do such ease
hmm okay secondary archetype knows I'm
not sure if I agree with that but did I
do you know video swing yeah okay you're
brilliant okay so second archetype is
that what you can do but takes more of
an effort and it often has some more
theatrical fields hooked mm-hmm okay
secondary archetype is something is
useful because the guy who asked the
primary archetype might die and we need
somebody to fill his role we take
somebody that's the second archetype
could put him in the church their
secondary archetype is also
communicating because it means you
understand the guys that have that as
their first architect don't example you
can be a woman in a room for the men but
you can be the woman who can communicate
with the men are up to
- the women successfully we need to be
the gay guy who gets along well with the
women and you can explain to the men for
example what the women are up to women
are up to you're not you are a man
you're not a woman but precisely because
you're gay and you see the world through
women size you can successfully transfer
that is knowledge to the tribe and to us
- okay so second our archetype is often
communicated has a theatrical quality to
it but if you're lucky in life you
probably get to explore both your
primary and your secondary archetype you
can do them in any order so um so you
need music between 23 and on til six
years ago until it was 52
that's your secondary archetype that was
I started my secondary archetype knowing
I couldn't do philosoph until I was at
least 40 years old so I did music for
years and by doing my second archetype
and becoming a successful music producer
and artists and making music I learned
popular culture I learned the world we
live in
I learned media I learned mass medium
did it all the difference between the
two and I know how hard it is to be a
good artist I know how hard it is to be
successful artist I'm highest respect
for artists I love art I love music I
love literature I love all the different
fields of art I even did theater myself
okay love them to bits yeah when I was
39 I got the chance to become a
philosopher wrote my first book and I
tell you what he was kind of hard to
understand first then I got it this is
my real element huh
this is where I shine this is abstract
thinking that's my thing and they
release that god I'm lucky I'm so
fucking lucky I had great parents great
upbringing and self-confidence and had
these two talents when I was seven years
old my boys from one side was rock stars
the other satis philosophers had beards
I think that's a rare coming together of
two archetypes like it's not often that
the the rock star is also a philosopher
you know they should be more often I
need to vogner is the combo is the comma
again so so no a lot for most of it's an
art form in itself so the tertiary art
form is the opposite of poetry it's a
literary art form so so so that sued my
mind and and I'd be honest with you this
is dirty secret okay I'm not really good
at anything else besides the two things
you know my job's nothing I understand
that he's functional got a cleaning lady
coming over didn't care me I love her
yeah I'm not pretty good at anything
else except these two things so they
have the time I'm barely functional
myself I just I somehow managed to get
by yeah outside of those other passions
that I have you know I'm involved with
the men's movement in Europe and we work
in your 14 countries and our common
friend David foolery does the same thing
in the UK we rebel wisdom we Scandinavia
with our network here and it's
incredibly rewarding to work with these
young men you usually found us through
Jordan Peter so they may be heard me and
a podcast some worth suddenly they join
the movement in the ring and teaching
the guys archetypes is incredibly
rewarding teaching them the first
archetype second archetype and then the
original archetypes and compare them
with possible modern archetypes right
now we're developing modern archetypes a
there might be professions but may also
be other meaningful purposeful
purposeful things that men do so it's
what we're aiming at is to give each guy
an archetype that works for him mm-hmm
and hopefully give him some kind of
contributing role that seems like a
great educational project doesn't it I
mean and they have to be involved
themselves we don't know the map modern
archetypes yeah we told him we don't
know the answers no you have to develop
this yourself you have to work on it and
we don't know if you're gonna find an
archetype that suits you that gives you
a contributed role and we know for sure
that really that excites me that idea
because you know I'm sure and I see all
these kids you know all the time
and they don't have a they don't know
what their fucking role is they're so
bloody lost it's just unbelievable right
yeah it's so so as if they had if they
had archetypes to work with and if they
could be conscious of that in some sense
that would be real education wouldn't it
well it's all called tribal mapping
that's what I'm working with a camera to
Liberto coming out of it that's gonna be
the big thing coming out of this book
we're essentially formulating a whole
new way of doing anthropology called
tribal anthropology based on data on
facts and we'll be discoveries that we
got the inner circuit dominated by the
women we got the outer circuit dominated
by the men it's a metric and it Patrick
II for lack of better words and and
they're equal and they have different
responsibilities and one of them pushes
and one of them pulls okay it's it's
some and they've got androgynous in
between we need them too yeah the
problem is have got a lot of guys who we
don't automatically find roles for today
and this is the honest brutal truth of
the men's movement today we cannot
guarantee that we gonna find a
contributed role for you as young men
and if you don't find it yourself even
with their help you're probably gonna
blow up and kill yourself at the end of
the day cuz they don't men do if they
don't find purpose yeah at best you find
a really dominant woman who wants a toy
boy yeah and she can have the purpose
you can sort of say it along with that
that's being assistant to a powerful
woman could be the only option you got
laughs let's do it that from God said
find some kind of role on the overall
tribal map of contemporary society and
your life's gonna be full with purpose
and meaning and you'll be happy if you
don't find it we know guys when they
become redundant they start drinking and
they hang themselves yeah and one sign
that there's a crisis in masculinity is
that we're gonna have a huge male
bipolarity
epidemic over the next 10 years watch
out for that one
are we already there I mean yeah we're
ready there yeah the best young man I
work with all come to me and they
already have the diagnosis
and I tell them you you know you're not
sick at all it's just a healthy reaction
to a very unhealthy society and a
pathological society where men in their
masculinity are not being appreciated
and while the society is trying to
castrate you and for children you need
to get out of that quickly you need to
find your masculinity spend more time in
nature and this is the opposite message
that everybody's receiving isn't it it's
like it's a precise opposite that's true
I think yeah that's the conclusion I
came to being a you know sensitive
new-age guy right it's like no it's not
that it's like it's that's its that's
that's all a mistake
yeah first advice I give these guys that
get out in nature build to tend
somewhere and hopefully live in Canada
or Sweden you got lots of nature
everywhere it's accessible to you and
just build tent and bring your friends
out there doing a hunting club or
something like that
you learn from the older men what it
means to be a man and go hunting you'll
discover you love learning people and
martial arts martial art martial I was
thinking that as well martial arts man
should do martial arts all the time it's
always like you know the guys have gone
to the gym on their own yeah if you
think that if you touch another guy
you're homosexual
yeah no you're not no yes okay you need
to be physical with other men you need
to go to martial arts club and you need
to get out of the loop where you go to
the gym and you just work in front of a
mirror encouraging your own art system
no your Instagram picture and your
tinder paper I was doing using your body
being totally isolated being I sit in
this way and trying to fuck the women
all the time is gonna make you a girl
chase you're gonna make it pathetic the
women are gonna turn it down and show
you the men are not gonna make friends
with you you know understand why you're
a loser all of a sudden because you did
the wrong thing from the very start
no you need to collaborate with other
guys and the best way to do that if
you're physiologically stressed is to go
to martial arts club and learn martial
arts mm-hmm okay okay let's see what the
guys now while we work on the market
type soon we'll see houses cus will be
my baby you don't know mm-hmm we don't
know if you can find our guitars for the
vast majority I so whether we can't